Hey everyone and thanks for jumping back
into the macroverse.
Today we're going to talk about the most
recent speech given by Kevin Worsh at
Jacksonhole. If you guys like the
content, make sure you subscribe to the
channel, give the video a thumbs up, and
check out the sale on Into the
Cryptoverse Premium at into the
cryptoverse.com.
As a reminder, the prices for tickets uh
for the first ITC conference taking
place November 21st, those prices are
going to be going up uh in just a few
days on September 1st. So, make sure you
get your ticket before then if you would
like to go. Link is in the description
below or the pinned comment. So, I know
like me, many of you dreamed of
analyzing
the the the the chair of the Federal
Reserve speech is at Jackson Hole when
you were a little kid, right? We all
dreamed of it and and here we are. Uh
but it it it's not that surprising,
right? I mean he he essentially came out
and you know he was quite hawkish talked
about how inflation is not really giving
him the reads that would make him think
like they have it under control and I
believe he said something to the effect
of he would you know he'd be hardressed
to to say that monetary policy is
restrictive right now like it's not is
is what he was saying and and so because
of that it it certainly it certainly led
to at least in the short term of
repricing of, you know, potential
interest rates and like what those
probabilities are. So, we'll talk about
that in a little bit, but I I do want to
say one other thing before we get into
the interest rate stuff, and that is
like we keep looking at interest rates
and and we talk a lot about interest
rates, but and whether they're going to
hike, whether they're whether they're
going to cut. Um, but there's another
tool that the Fed has, and obviously it
was a main theme of the last cycle, and
I'm sure many of you remember it,
probably not so fondly, and that is
quantitative tightening or QT. I think a
lot of people just kind of assume that
QE has to come back, right? Like it it
just has to come back in the short term
because that's what they do. But given
the technological boom of artificial
intelligence and AI and if we are to
believe that the AI um bull market
continues into into the next year, which
I I think it will even with a correction
in the back half of the midterm year, if
you are to believe that, and one of the
reasons I believe that is just simply
nothing more than I don't believe the
market will top before you get all these
major IPOs out of the way. And I mean
Anthropics is probably coming up in the
next month or two, but Open AI is
probably not until 2027. So if you
believe in that
that that will continue, then the
argument is that could they actually
start quantitative tightening once
again. So I I think you know if you look
at Wars' history, he's already he he's
known to to want to reduce the balance
sheet of the Fed, right? like that is
one of the things he has been known for
uh wanting to do in the past. And he
also does not view quantitative
tightening necessarily as a substitute
for interest rates. Um I I think that
you know some people think like oh if if
we just do aggressive QT then we don't
actually have to raise rates. Now, it is
true that you could have a situation
where if they were to go through QT, it
might eventually lead to outcomes where
interest rates don't necessarily have to
be as high. But I also think in the
short term, Wars basically did what he
had to do because if you think back to
um the last FOMC meeting, or maybe it
wasn't the FOMC, maybe it was some other
speech that he gave, but if you listen
back to some of his prior speeches, one
of the things that he said was that they
were going to rely on the long end of
the yield curve to to do the work for
them rather than necessarily raising
rates, right? rather than changing the
short end of the yield curve um they
would rely on the long end of the yield
curve. But something major happened
between when he said that and today and
that is that the Treasury Secretary
Bessant you know they in they definitely
accelerated their bond buyback program.
So, and and and the point of that the
point of what the Treasury Secretary is
trying to do is they're trying to bring
down the long end of the yield curve at
the same time that the chair of the
Federal Reserve is saying, "No, we need
to rely on the long end of the yield
curve." So, how can both be true? How
can you rely on the long end of the
yield curve? like you know one branch or
you know one institution
but then the other institution comes in
and says no we're going to we're going
to purposely try to keep long end rates
down. Now the problem with the bond
buyback program is that it doesn't
necessarily solve any of the issues that
led to inflation in the first place. It
doesn't solve any of them. In fact, you
could argue it's actually inflationary.
And so what you might see is you might
see the market tests the Fed's resolve
or or the the Treasury Secretaries
resolve because when when governments
intervene in in markets like that,
right? When they start intervening, the
market has a habit of like testing their
resolve constantly and and sort of
forcing their hand to see, all right,
you'll do that. Well, how far will you
go to defend the long end of the old
curve? So I I just want to put this, you
know, this like nugget in your brain a
and that is
QT
might be announced in the coming months.
I I don't think it's going to be
announced in in September. Uh like I
don't think it's going to start in
September. I don't really think it would
start in October. the and I could be
wrong, but the earliest I could see
quantitative tightening being announced
would be December of 2026 because that
would be one year after when they
suspended it. And I I I think if they're
going to raise rates, they might not
want to announce both at the same time,
right? Like I don't know that they're
going to say, "All right, we're going to
raise rates and also we're going to
start QT." They might try to stagger
that.
A more realistic time frame on when QT
could start back up would be early 2027.
That's probably the base case, but I
think there is a case to be made that it
actually could start as as soon as
December or at least an announcement of
it as soon as December. Now, listen, if
they do that, that doesn't mean like
that's the nail in the coffin for a
potential Bitcoin bull market, right?
What it means is that the next bull
market
in crypto might be similar to the last
one where Bitcoin does well and it lifts
some of the altcoins up but the majority
of the altcoin market just collectively
bleeds back to Bitcoin, right? Like
there's a case to be made that we just
get another one of those just because
and and it could be a scenario where the
next four-year cycle for Bitcoin, the
first part of the cycle is during QT,
but maybe the latter part of the cycle
is during QE. That's actually what
happened in 2019, right? Like the first
part of the cycle was during
quantitative tighting and you know they
went a little too far. Maybe not, but I
mean the pandemic happened and then they
had to pivot over to QE. So I I just
want you to think about that kind of
like in the back of your mind that
something similar could happen again.
It's possible that they can announce
quantitative tightening and and if they
do um you know it it could have a
similar effect on markets that it had
last cycle just kind of running the same
playbook once again. And a lot of people
learned their lesson last cycle as to
what that means for higher risk assets.
And so I I wouldn't be surprised if if
that is the outcome where you get a rate
hike uh at some point they actually
start quantitative tightening back up
not because we're you know in a bare
market right but because the AI trade is
still going on and and this is their way
to try to tame inflation because the one
thing Kevin Wars does not want to do is
allow inflation to run rampant. He's
already been very critical of of you
know the prior Fed chair in some ways
and basically just saying look we just
allowed inflation to run above target
for the last 5 years. I don't think he's
super excited about the idea of
inflation just coming right back because
then he's essentially doing what he's
criticizing his predecessors of doing.
So, I don't know if he'll be successful,
but I I do think that is is something to
consider as to how this may in fact play
out. So, what I want to do as well is I
want to look here at um uh let me see if
I can show the screen. So, I want to
look here at our rates. So, this is what
expectations for rate hikes were looking
like before
Jackson Hole, right? So before the
meeting, uh there was a about a 2/3
chance that they would keep rates steady
in September and about a 1/3 chance that
they would that they would actually uh
raise rates. But now you can see that
the probabilities have kind of flipped
where there's almost a 2/3 chance of a
rate hike and only a one-/ird chance
that they keep rates constant. Now there
are some more things that will happen
between now and then that will affect
these probabilities. For instance, we
will have another labor market report
next week. Uh we'll have you know
another inflation print in midepptember
as well. So this is by no means like
locked in here. It could certainly
change but this is a consideration here,
right? because the market right now
thinks there's actually going to be two
rate hikes um this year or at least
leaning towards two rate hikes this
year. And then I wonder if 2027
uh they might start quantitative
tightening back up to try and help
reduce inflation and and you know and
then they probably wouldn't continue to
raise rates. I'm not convinced yet that
they're going to raise to to 4.25. I I
think raising to four is might be enough
to kind of, you know, kind of steady the
ship a little bit. That doesn't mean
like I I they can't raise, but I I I'd
be surprised
uh if they if they didn't at least
consider that a little bit more. And
then in the mid9s, they actually cut
rates and and then they reignited the
animal spirits and and then what
happened is they ended up raising rates
25 basis points and then they just left
it. They left it at 25 basis point rate
hike at for like the next year or
something and now eventually they had to
raise rates again that eventually killed
the uh the dotcom bubble but that
process was like a three-year process. I
mean it took place over a really really
long period of time. So
right now it it looks like the Fed
according to the markets is more so
leaning in the direction of a rate hike.
Um, but again, there's still plenty of
time to go between now and then. So, in
terms of the thesis that that you know
that I've talked about on this channel
and and what I think is going to happen,
remember the stock market will often
have corrections in the back half of
midterm years. And often times the
correction in the stock market will
start in either August or September.
Now, in two of those years, in 2018 and
2014, when the stock market started
correcting in September, it wasn't
really obvious that we were in a
correction until October. So, there's no
guarantee that we're going to get into
September and be like, "Oh, yeah, like
this this is what's happening." In in a
couple of those cases, it wasn't really
even obvious that this is what was
happening until until September. And you
can actually look at it, right? If we if
I show you the S&P 500 in uh 20 uh 2014,
you can see that it it topped the week
of September 15th, right? And and you
know, we didn't get this big red candle
down until about early to mid-occtober.
And then if you look at at 2018, you can
see that the market found a top the week
of September 17th, but it was still
basically almost at new highs even the
week of October 1st, right? It wasn't
until the second week of October where
it was more clear that we were in fact
getting a correction. Now, in 2022, the
correction started, you know, shortly
before the the meeting at Jackson Hole.
I remember it vividly. This was the week
of August 15th is when we found the
local top. And then shortly after Powell
came out uh and gave his speech at
Jackson Hole and I still remember it as
I'm sure many of you guys do as well
where he basically said there will be
pain. And he said that and then the
market then proceeded to sell off into
the month of October. So you know it's
hard to say right like exactly where
there might be a local top if this plays
out like whether it could be August
whether it could be September. But if if
you needed a narrative for what would
justify a 10 to 20% drop, you know, a
late cycle rate hike might be just
enough to do it. In fact, again, as I
was talking about earlier, if you look
at at interest rates in in the '9s,
right? So, if we if we zoom all the way
back over here, I thought I added it,
but maybe I need to add it again. Uh, if
you look at at rates,
I'm not hanging on getting it to load
here. So, let me go over here.
All right. So, we're going to go to the
S&P and then we're going to add interest
rates. So, if you look at interest rates
in the9s,
let me uh flip this over to a new scale.
Imagine for a moment that I actually
edited my videos and you guys didn't
have to watch me do this. Like, imagine.
We will never know, though, right? We'll
never know what that's like. Um, so if
you look in uh the '9s,
zoom all the way back, you can see that
they they had gone through this rate
hiking cycle and then they cut rates
kind of like they have in this cycle.
And then they ended up raising rates
again, right, in in March of 1997. And
when they raised rates in March of 97,
the stock market actually started
correcting in February, right? It
started correcting the month before they
raised rates. And back then it dropped
about 10%. Right? So you got an
approximately 10% drop in stocks with
the rate hike. Probably people thought
it was over, right? Because it probably
felt like at the time that that was the
worst thing in the world to have another
rate hike after cutting rates from, you
know, 6% down to down to 5.25. And then
they raised rates back up to five and a
half.
And then they kept them there from March
of 97 through August of 98. So a year
and a half rates stayed constant. Then
they lowered rates in a correction and
then they ended up having to raise rates
again. And then finally the dot bubble
burst.
So it it took a long time, right? It
took a very long time for that to play
out. So what I'm saying is if they were
to raise rates in September or at some
point, you know, maybe that is what you
need to to justify just that brief
correction in the stock market, kind of
reset sentiment in the crypto space in
the in the fourth quarter of the midterm
year, how it normally plays out and and
then things just kind of carry on like
they always have. And then yeah, maybe
at some point in the next couple of
years, uh, things could change, but
again, that could still be a ways out,
right? Like I don't, you know, it could
still be another year or two away before
we're that phase of of the business
cycle. But those are my thoughts.
Hopefully you guys have found this stuff
useful. If you guys like the content,
make sure you subscribe, give the video
a thumbs up, remember to check out uh
the ITC conference is coming up uh in
November. But if you get if you want to
get your ticket before prices go up,
make sure you do so uh before September
1st. Thank you guys for tuning in and
I'll see you next time.